Guide to the Paul Hamilton Hayne papers, 1815-1944 and undated RL.00523
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Paul Hamilton Hayne papers
1815-1944 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Hayne, Paul Hamilton, 1830-1886
RL.00523
13.8 Linear Feet
about 4930 items
Paul Hamilton Hayne was a white Southern American poet and literary critic from Charleston, S.C., and Columbia County, Georgia. He supported the Confederacy and opposed Reconstruction in the post-war South. The collection consists of correspondence, diaries, notes, scrapbooks, clippings, and literary manuscripts of Hayne and his family. The papers illustrate Hayne's career and his personal and political views.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Paul Hamilton Hayne Papers was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase from 1944-2000.
Biographical Note
Paul Hamilton Hayne was a white Southern American poet and literary critic from Charleston, S.C., and Columbia County, Georgia. He supported the Confederacy and opposed Reconstruction in the post-war South.
Collection Overview
Collection consists of correspondence, diaries, notes, scrapbooks, clippings, and literary manuscripts of Hayne and his family. The papers illustrate Hayne's career and refer to Russell's Magazine (which Hayne edited), literary criticism, Southern writers, American literature, politics, Reconstruction in South Carolina, Civil War conditions, fears of Black or enslaved peoples' rebellions, poor economic conditions for white Southerners, and general antagonism towards the writings of Walt Whitman and William Dean Howells. Includes Hayne's diaries (1864-1884), largely composed of comments on correspondence received, notations of ideas and events, and manuscript copies of poems, many autographed, by Hayne's son, William Hamilton Hayne.
Major correspondents include Edward Bok, Jefferson Davis, Charles A. E. Gayarré, Oliver Wendell Holmes, Sidney Lanier, Henry Wadsworth Longfellow, Thomas Nelson Page, James Platt, Margaret Junkin Preston, Francis S. Saltus, William Gilmore Sims, Edmund C. Stedman, Alexander H. Stephens, Algernon C. Swinburne, Henry Timrod, Moses Colt Tyler, and John Greenleaf Whittier.
The addition (accession #2000-0273) (250 items; 2.2 linear feet, dated 1831-1886, contains transcriptions of selected letters, typed and annotated by Rayburn Moore as he edited A Man of Letters in the Nineteenth-century South (1982). Many of the original letters may be found in Duke University's David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library.
Georgia -- Columbia County; South Carolina -- Charleston; Authors, American; Transcripts; Authors -- Correspondence; Authors -- Diaries; Southern States -- Intellectual life; American literature -- History and criticism; Reconstruction (U.S. history, 1865-1877) -- South Carolina; Hayne, William Hamilton; Bok, Edward William, 1863-1930; Hayne, Paul Hamilton, 1830-1886; Gayarré, Charles, 1805-1895; Page, Thomas Nelson, 1853-1922; Longfellow, Henry Wadsworth, 1807-1882; Lanier, Sidney, 1842-1881; Holmes, Oliver Wendell, 1809-1894; Sims, William Gilmore, 1806-1870; Saltus, Francis Saltus, 1849-1889; Preston, Margaret Junkin, 1820-1897; Platt, James, b. 1831; Timrod, Henry, 1828-1867; Swinburne, Algernon Charles, 1837-1909; Stephens, Alexander Hamilton, 1812-1883; Stedman, Edmund Clarence, 1833-1908; Tyler, Moses Coit, 1835-1900; Whittier, John Greenleaf, 1807-1892; Davis, Jefferson, 1808-1809
- Correspondence Series, 1815-1927 and undated
  Existence and Location of Copies note
  Transcriptions of letters from 1831-1886, typed and annotated by Rayburn Moore, exist. Please see the container list for accession# 2000-0273.
  - 1815-1867 (Box 1)
  - 1868-1872 (Box 2)
  - 1873-1875 (Box 3)
  - 1876-1878 (Box 4)
  - 1879-1880 (Box 5)
  - 1881 (Box 6)
  - 1882-1883 April (Box 7)
  - 1883 May-1884 (Box 8)
  - 1885 (Box 9)
  - 1886 (Box 10)
  - 1887-1890 (Box 11)
  - 1891-1907 (Box 12)
  - 1908-1927 and undated; includes undated fragments (Box 13)
- Diaries Series, 1864-1885
  - 1864-1885 (Box 14)
- Scrapbooks Series
  - Scrapbooks (Box 15-18)
- Miscellaneous Series
  - Financial papers (Box 19)
  - Correspondence from transcriber of Hayne's letters (Box 19)
  - Photographs (Box 19)
- Clippings Series
  - A-Q (Box 20)
  - R-Z (Box 21)
  - Contemporary authors (Box 22)
  - Miscellaneous papers (Box 22)
  - P.H. Hayne (Box 23-24)
  - Literary criticisms (Box 25)
  - War reminiscences (Box 25)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 26)
- Writings Series
  - Works: A-S (Box 27)
  - Works: T-Z (Box 28)
  - Last Poems (Box 28)
  - Wickham's Roost (Box 28)
  - Misc., unidentified (Box 28)
- Miscellaneous
  - Biographical materials (Box 29)
  - Genealogy (Box 29)
  - Tributes (Box 29)
  - Works of contemporary authors (Box 29)
- Preliminary Container List for Accession #2000-0273
  - Transcriptions of selected correspondence
    Scope and Contents note
    Typed and annotated by Rayburn Moore, editor of A Man of Letters in the Nineteenth-Century South: The Selected Letters of Paul Hamilton Hayne, 1982
    - 1831 May 10-1881 Feb. 5 (Box 1)
    - 1881 Feb. 8-1883 Aug. 23 (Box 2)
    - 1883 Aug. 30-1885 Apr. 17 (Box 3)
    - 1885 Apr. 19-1886 Nov. 13 (Box 4)